Guide to the Liberation News Service Photographs PHOTOS.022
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Liberation News Service Photographs
1965-1981
bulk
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Liberation News Service (New York, N.Y.).
PHOTOS.022
7.5 Linear Feet in 15 manuscript boxes.
The Liberation News Service (LNS) (1967-1981), a left-wing news agency, offered its subscribers, mostly college and underground newspapers, news packets, including photographs, twice a week. Journalists and photographers from the United States and around the world supplied the LNS with stories and images documenting the progressive movements and counterculture of the 1960s and 1970s. Half the collection covers the United States, with emphasis on anti-war (Vietnam) protest, the civil rights and women’s liberation movements, and youth culture. International coverage focuses on national liberation movements, with emphasis on Vietnam and China.
around 7200 photographs: black and white; 8x10 inches
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Liberation News Service was established by Marshall Bloom and Raymond Mungo in 1967, after they had been fired from the staff of the U.S. Student Press Association (located in Washington, DC), for their radical political views. In 1968 the LNS moved to New York City, and absorbed the Student Communications Network (founded by the University Christian Movement). The LNS had several hundred subscribers, most college, underground and progressive community newspapers, to which it supplied twice-weekly packets containing current news, features, opinion pieces, poetry, photographs, cartoons and artwork that documented the progressive movements and counterculture of the 1960s and 1970s. The LNS print shop made its facilities available to other left-wing organizations. The LNS went out of business in 1981.
Sources:
Young, Allen, "Liberation News Service," Encyclopedia of the American Left(Chicago: University of Illinois Press, 1992), 422-424.
Other Finding Aids note
Additional information can be found in the
appendix, LNS Photographers
, that is linked to this guide. This consists of lists of those credited—drawn from the credit stamps or inscriptions on the backs of the photographs themselves. From these lists, researchers can locate photographs in the collection that are credited to individual photographers, news or photograph agencies.
Scope and Content Note
The collection of about 7,200 8x10 black and white glossy photographs consists of images of both national and international political and social events, issues, and organizations. They were shot by more than 300 freelance photographers or photographers for other news agencies, many from outside the United States, including more than two dozen Vietnamese photographers.
Arrangement
Missing Title
I, International
II, United States
Folders are arranged alphabetically by region and country within Series I, and alphabetically by subject within Series II.
The files are grouped into 2 series:
Related Material
Liberation News Service Records (Temple University Library Contemporary Culture Collection. Philadelphia, PA); Marshall Bloom Alternative Press Collection, Amherst College Library, Massachusetts (collection includes copies of approximately 25,000 alternative "underground" newspapers, most originally compiled by LNS as record copies from its subscribers); finding aid available at:
Marshall Bloom Alternative Press Collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Tamiment Library purchased the Liberation News Service Photographs from the Liberation News Service in 1986. The accession number associated with this gift is 1950.176.
African Americans |v Pictorial works.; Wounded Knee (S.D.) |x History |x Indian occupation, 1973 |v Pictorial works.; Women -- United States -- Pictorial works.; Vietnam |v Pictorial works.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 |x Protest Movements |z United States |v Pictorial works.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 |v Pictorial works.; South Africa |v Pictorial works.; Cuba |v Pictorial works.; China |v Pictorial works.; Black-and-white photographs.; African Americans |x Civil rights |v Pictorial works.; Black Panther Party. -- |v Pictorial works; Bloom, Marshall, 1944-1969; Miss America Pageant.; Mungo, Raymond, 1946-; National Venceremos Brigade.; Rolling Stones.; Vietnam Veterans Against the War.; Weather Underground Organization.; Young Lords Party.
- Series I: International (Box not specified, Folder data_value_missing_4c537b82ca2290671dcefd1ae89376bd)
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I: International covers principally national liberation movements and events in Asia, Africa, and Latin America, with the greatest coverage going to Vietnam, China, Cuba (includes the Venceremos Brigade), and South Africa.
  - Un-numbered folders, undated (Box not specified, Folder data_value_missing_a1a615d42afb4a6c2db03ed399112f48)
  - Africa: General, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Angola, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Appalachia: (see mining), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Argentina, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Biafra, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bolivia, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Burma, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cambodia, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cambodia, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Canada, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chile, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Chile, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Chile, undated (Box 1, Folder 12.1)
  - China Features: Culture (art, theatre, literary), undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - China Features, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - China Features: Economy, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - China Features: Education, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - China Features: Environment, Cities, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - China Features: Housing, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - China Features: Industry, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - China Features: Medical, Health Care, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - China Features: Military, Police, Politics, Anti-War, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - China Features: Sports, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - China Features: Women, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - China Features: Workers, Peasants, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - China, undated (Box 3, Folder 24.1)
  - Chine, undated (Box 3, Folder 24.2)
  - China, undated (Box 3, Folder 24.3)
  - China, undated (Box 3, Folder 24.4)
  - Congo Brazzaville, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Cuba: El Grito, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Cuba: Prensa Catina, undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Cuba: Venceremos Brigade, Folder 1 of 2, undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Cuba: Venceremos Brigade, Folder 2 of 2, undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Cuba, Folder 1 of 2, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Cuba, Folder 2 of 2, undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Denmark, undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Dominican Republic, undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - England, undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Eritrea/Ethiopia, undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Ecuador, undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - France, Folder 1 of 3, undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - France, Folder 2 of 3, undated (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - France, Folder 3 of 3, undated (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Germany, undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Guam, undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Guinea Bissau, undated (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Holland, undated (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Iran, Folder 1 of 2, undated (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Iran, Folder 2 of 2, undated (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Ireland, Folder 1 of 2, undated (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Ireland, Folder 2 of 2, undated (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Israel, undated (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Italy, undated (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Indian Subcontinent/Pakistan, undated (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Japan, undated (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Korea, Democratic Peoples Republic of (North Korea), undated (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Korea, Republic of (South Korea), undated (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Latin America, Folder 1 of 2, undated (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Latin America, Folder 2 of 2, undated (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Latin America: El Salvador, undated (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Latin America: maps and miscellaneous, undated (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Laos, Folder 1 of 3, undated (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Laos, Folder 2 of 3, undated (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Laos, Folder 3 of 3, undated (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Middle East, undated (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - Morocco, undated (Box 6, Folder 62.1)
  - Mozambique, undated (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - Palestinians, undated (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Peru, undated (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - Philippines, undated (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - Portugal, undated (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Sahara, undated (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - South Africa, Folder 1 of 2, undated (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - South Africa, Folder 2 of 2, undated (Box 7, Folder 69.1)
  - South East Asia, undated (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - Soviet Union, undated (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Spain, undated (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Sweden, undated (Box 7, Folder 72.1)
  - Taiwan, undated (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - Thailand, undated (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - Turkey, undated (Box 7, Folder 75)
  - Uruguay, undated (Box 7, Folder 76)
  - Virgin Islands, undated (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - Vietnam, undated (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - Vietnam, undated (Box 8, Folder 79)
  - Vietnam, undated (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - Vietnam, American Presence, undated (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - Vietnam, Atrocities, undated (Box 8, Folder 84)
  - Vietnam, Atrocities, undated (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - Vietnam, Combat, undated (Box 8, Folder 86)
  - Vietnam, Combat, undated (Box 8, Folder 87)
  - Vietnam, Hanoi, undated (Box 8, Folder 88)
  - Vietnam, Ho Chi Minh, undated (Box 8, Folder 89)
  - Vietnam, North, Folder 1 of 2, undated (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - Vietnam, North, Folder 2 of 2, undated (Box 9, Folder 91)
  - Vietnam, North: Anne Dockery’s trip, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 92)
  - Vietnam, North Defensive, undated (Box 9, Folder 93)
  - Vietnam, North: Education & Culture, undated (Box 9, Folder 94)
  - Vietnam, North & South, Early 1970s. Folder 1 of 2. (Box 9, Folder 95)
  - Vietnam, North & South, Early 1970s. Folder 2 of 2. (Box 9, Folder 96)
  - Vietnam, Postcards, undated (Box 9, Folder 97)
  - Vietnam, PRG Territory, undated (Box 9, Folder 98)
  - Vietnamese people, undated (Box 10, Folder 99)
  - Vietnam, Post Liberation, undated (Box 10, Folder 100)
  - Vietnam, Prisoners in South, undated (Box 10, Folder 101)
  - Vietnam, South cities, undated (Box 10, Folder 102)
  - Vietnam, Thieu government, undated (Box 10, Folder 103)
  - Zimbabwe, undated (Box 10, Folder 104)
- Series II: United States (Box not specified, Folder data_value_missing_b4ffb365d53f13c3a503504594328879)
  Series II: United States focuses on protest against the war in Vietnam, the civil rights and women's liberation movements and other movements and populations, including gay liberation, Chicanos, environmental activism, the labor movement, G.I. movement, Puerto Rican community activism, and political prisoners. There are several folders containing images of individuals, principally leftists, government officials, and celebrities, including the Rolling Stones. Organizations represented include the Black Panther Party, the Young Lords, Vietnam Veterans Against the War, and the Weathermen (aka Weather Underground). Notable images include a small, but significant group of photographs of the later-famous Women’s Liberation demonstration at the 1968 Miss America pageant (in the "Women—Sexism" folder). Disappointingly, one folder labeled "Demonstrations--Kent State" does not contain images of the images Kent State University anti-Vietnam War demonstration of 1970 (in which National Guardsmen fired upon students), but instead date from a 1977 commemoration of the original event.
  - Aged, Folder 1 of 2, undated (Box 10, Folder 105)
  - Aged, Folder 2 of 2, undated (Box 10, Folder 106)
  - Agri business, undated (Box 10, Folder 107)
  - Alternative Lifestyles, undated (Box 10, Folder 108)
  - Alternative Lifestyles, Religious sects, undated (Box 11, Folder 109)
  - Anti-Imperialist demonstrations: U.S., undated (Box 11, Folder 110)
  - Anti-War and Civil Rights Demonstrations: Cornell University and other locations, undated (Box 11, Folder 111)
  - Anti-War and Civil Rights Demonstrations: Cornell University and other locations, undated (Box 11, Folder 115)
  - Anti-War Demonstrations, undated (Box 11, Folder 112)
  - Anti-War Demonstrations: Boston/Cambridge, undated (Box 11, Folder 113)
  - Anti-War Demonstrations: California, undated (Box 11, Folder 114)
  - Anti-War Movement: Columbia University, undated (Box 11, Folder 116)
  - Anti-War Movement: Misc. Demos., undated (Box 11, Folder 117)
  - Anti-War Movement: New York, undated (Box 11, Folder 118)
  - Anti-War Movement: Wash. D.C., Mayday, undated (Box 11, Folder 119)
  - Anti-War: Santa Barbara, undated (Box 12, Folder 120)
  - Art, undated (Box 12, Folder 121)
  - Asian Americans, undated (Box 12, Folder 122)
  - Black Americans, Folder 1 of 3, undated (Box 12, Folder 123)
  - Black Americans, Folder 2 of 3, undated (Box 12, Folder 124)
  - Black Americans, Folder 3 of 3, undated (Box 12, Folder 125)
  - Black Panthers: General, undated (Box 12, Folder 126)
  - Black Panthers: Individuals, undated (Box 12, Folder 127)
  - Blacks: Southern U.S., undated (Box 12, Folder 128)
  - Blacks: Southern U.S. (Fayette Co., Tenn.), 1979 (Box 13, Folder 129)
  - Blacks: Southern U.S. (cotton picking, Fayette Co., Tenn.), 1979 (Box 13, Folder 130)
  - Blacks: Southern U.S. (Mississippi), Folder 1 of 2, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 131)
  - Blacks: Southern U.S. (Mississippi), Folder 2 of 2, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 132)
  - Blacks: Southern U.S. (Woodcutters, Mississippi), 1973 (Box 13, Folder 133)
  - Chicano, Folder 1 of 2, undated (Box 13, Folder 134)
  - Chicano, Folder 2 of 2, undated (Box 13, Folder 135)
  - Children/Youth, Folder 1 of 2, undated (Box 14, Folder 136)
  - Children/Youth, Folder 2 of 2, undated (Box 14, Folder 137)
  - Cities, undated (Box 14, Folder 137.1)
  - Civil Rights Movement, Poor People’s Campaign, undated (Box 14, Folder 138)
  - Consumerism: Advertising, undated (Box 14, Folder 139)
  - Corporations: Industry, undated (Box 14, Folder 140)
  - Cultural Events I: Music (non-celebrity), undated (Box 14, Folder 141)
  - Cultural Events II: Theatre, Guerilla theatre (non-celebrity), undated (Box 14, Folder 142)
  - Cultural Events III: Misc. (non-music, theatre), undated (Box 15, Folder 143)
  - Day Care, undated (Box 15, Folder 144)
  - Demonstrations: Anti-War, Poor Peoples march, undated (Box 15, Folder 145)
  - Demonstrations: Kent State, 1977 (Box 15, Folder 146)
  - Demonstrations: Misc., Folder 1 of 2, undated (Box 15, Folder 147)
  - Demonstrations: Misc., Folder 2 of 2, undated (Box 15, Folder 148)
  - Economy: Cutbacks, unemployment, welfare, undated (Box 15, Folder 149)
  - Education, Folder 1 of 3, undated (Box 16, Folder 150)
  - Education, Folder 2 of 3, undated (Box 16, Folder 151)
  - Education, Folder 3 of 3, undated (Box 16, Folder 152)
  - Environment, undated (Box 16, Folder 154)
  - Energy: US, undated (Box 16, Folder 155)
  - Farmworkers/United Farmworkers, undated (Box 16, Folder 156)
  - Food, undated (Box 16, Folder 157)
  - Gay, Folder 1of 3, undated (Box 17, Folder 158)
  - Gay, Folder 2 of 3, undated (Box 17, Folder 159)
  - Gay, Folder 3 of 3, undated (Box 17, Folder 160)
  - G.I. Movement, undated (Box 17, Folder 161)
  - Health, undated (Box 17, Folder 162)
  - Health: Sydenham Hospital, undated (Box 17, Folder 163)
  - Housing: Tenants, Folder 1 of 2, undated (Box 17, Folder 164)
  - Housing: Tenants, Folder 2 of 2, undated (Box 18, Folder 164.1)
  - Housing: Struggles, undated (Box 18, Folder 165)
  - Individuals, undated (Box 18, Folder 165.1)
  - Individuals I: the Left (US), Folder 1 of 3, undated (Box 18, Folder 166)
  - Individuals I: the Left (US), Folder 2 of 3, undated (Box 18, Folder 167)
  - Individuals I: the Left (US), Folder 3 of 3, undated (Box 18, Folder 168)
  - Individuals II: Government (US), Folder 1 of 2, undated (Box 18, Folder 169)
  - Individuals II: Government (US), Folder 2 of 2, undated (Box 18, Folder 170)
  - Individuals III: International, Left & Government 4, undated (Box 18, Folder 171)
  - Individuals IV: Celebrities, Music, Media, Etc., undated (Box 18, Folder 172)
  - Individuals IV: Celebrities, Music, Media, Etc., undated (Box 19, Folder 173)
  - Individuals IV: Celebrities, The Rolling Stones, undated (Box 19, Folder 174)
  - Klan/Anti-Klan, undated (Box 19, Folder 175)
  - Media: TV, Film, Printed, Radio, Non-Celebrity, undated (Box 19, Folder 176)
  - Military, undated (Box 19, Folder 177)
  - Mining, undated (Box 19, Folder 178)
  - Native Americans, undated (Box 20, Folder 179)
  - Native Americans: Wounded Knee: Other Demos, undated (Box 20, Folder 180)
  - New York City/Government, undated (Box 20, Folder 181)
  - Nuclear + Demos., undated (Box 20, Folder 181.1)
  - Occupational Health & Safety, undated (Box 20, Folder 182)
  - Organized Crime, undated (Box 20, Folder 183)
  - People: Misc., Crowds, undated (Box 20, Folder 184)
  - Police, undated (Box 21, Folder 185)
  - Police Intelligence/Agents, undated (Box 21, Folder 186)
  - Political Prisoners: Individuals & Support Demos, undated (Box 21, Folder 187)
  - Prisons, undated (Box 21, Folder 188)
  - Puerto Rico, undated (Box 21, Folder 189)
  - Puerto Ricans in U.S., undated (Box 21, Folder 190)
  - Puerto Ricans in U.S./Young Lords Party, undated (Box 22, Folder 191)
  - Rural America, undated (Box 22, Folder 192)
  - Technology, undated (Box 22, Folder 193)
  - Transportation, undated (Box 22, Folder 194)
  - U.S. Government 1980 Election/Convention & Demos, undated (Box 22, Folder 195)
  - U.S. Government Political Events: Miami Convention, 1972 (Box 22, Folder 196)
  - U.S. Government Political Events, 1973 (Box 22, Folder 197)
  - Underground/Weather includes Weathermen, SLA, undated (Box 22, Folder 198)
  - Unemployment: Welfare, undated (Box 22, Folder 199)
  - Veterans/Vietnam Veterans Against the War: Winter Soldier Organization, undated (Box 23, Folder 200)
  - Weathermen, undated (Box 23, Folder 201)
  - Women: General, undated (Box 23, Folder 202)
  - Women: Sexism, undated (Box 23, Folder 203)
  - Women: Working, undated (Box 23, Folder 204)
  - Workers (See Also Farm Workers, Health & Women), Folder 1 of 2, undated (Box 23, Folder 205)
  - Workers (See Also Farm Workers, Health & Women), Folder 2 of 2, undated (Box 24, Folder 206)
  - Workers: Auto, undated (Box 24, Folder 207)
  - Workers: Labor Movement, Folder 1 of 2, undated (Box 24, Folder 208)
  - Workers: Labor Movement, Folder 2 of 2, undated (Box 24, Folder 209)
  - Workers: Steel Industry, undated (Box 24, Folder 210)